From SVG to Canvas and Back

Samuli Kaipiainen

University of Helsinki, Department of Computer Science
samuli.kaipiainen@cs.helsinki.fi

Matti Paksula

Member of W3C SVG Interest Group

University of Helsinki, Department of Computer Science
matti.paksula@cs.helsinki.fi

University of Helsinki
Department of Computer Science

Gustaf Hällströmin katu 2b
00014 University of Helsinki
Helsinki
Finland

Abstract

In this paper we continue our previous work that was published at SVG Open 2009. We identify requirements for using SVG and Canvas effectively by using a trivial drawing application as a starting point. We will show that using browsers native rendering of SVG can be directly used as a bitmap export of SVG. This method has security issues that are briefly explained. Based on the feature requirements and security evaluation, we propose an API method for SVG elements that resembles the toDataURL()-method of Canvas. In addition, we propose a list of enhancements for browser manufacturers that were gathered during this work. Lastly, we list and evaluate SVG compatibility workarounds and combine everything that was presented in this paper to an interactive demonstration page.

Table of Contents TODO:check that it's final

Introduction
Motivation: Complete Drawing Application

Requirements for a Web Based Drawing Application

Our Implementations

Canvas to SVG
SVG to Canvas
Browser Compatibility

Security Issues

Same Origin and Canvas Origin Policy
Experimenting with Origin-Clean and Canvas

Recommendations

SVG.toDataURL() API
For Browser Manufacturers

SVG Compatibility Workarounds

Implementations with Canvas
Implementations with Flash
Problems with Workarounds

Guideline for Drawing Application Technologies

Guideline and the Demonstration Page
Guideline Evaluation

Conclusions
Bibliography

Introduction

At SVG Open 2009 we presented a method of using the bitmap content of Canvas element in SVG as an image element. This was done by utilizing canvas.toDataURL()-method that returns a base64-coded pixel representation of the canvas drawing context as a PNG image. This data URI can be set as source for a SVG Image element. In our demonstration we combined the best parts of SVG (vector drawing, native scene graph support) and Canvas (pixel drawing) in one trivial drawing application. SVG to Canvas transfer was done in server-side, by rasterizing the image and then drawing that on a canvas element [TRIVIAL09].

As the method for transferring Canvas to SVG was native in the browser (toDataURL()), the next step is obviously to do the same for SVG to Canvas instead of server-side conversion. It would be tempting to use browsers native rendering, but unfortunately SVG does not support a toDataURL()-method. There has been some discussion about adding same method to SVG, but this has some serious security issues that will be discussed in the "Security Issues" section of this paper.

In this paper we will show an experimental method for using the browsers native rendering support to render SVG on Canvas. We will also present a complete list of the possible methods for using SVG together with Canvas. Evaluation of these methods and application fits is also given. In addition, we present a list of recommendations for browser manufacturers to implement for improved support and adaptation of SVG and Canvas.

Motivation: Complete Drawing Application

Like in the paper we published last year, our motivation is drawing in the web: using the right techniques for the right things. (See "Combining existing components: SVG-Edit and CanvasPaint")

The need for interface between SVG and canvas is real and really required for efficent adaptation of SVG. For example, SVG-edits issue #70, "ability to save canvas as PNG" is currently solved with JavaScript+Canvas rendering workaround although a native implementation would be better [ISSUE70]. A list of rendering workarounds is given the "SVG Compatibility Workarounds" section of this paper.

Requirements for a Web Based Drawing Application

The following list shows requirements for a completely web based drawing application. This list does not apply only for drawing applications: if every requirement would be supported natively by the browsers, it would make the adaptation of SVG and Canvas more popular.

Pixel drawing

Vector drawing

Interfaces

Bitmap export and import (Canvas to SVG)

Vector rasterization and import (SVG to Canvas)

Exporting

Export vectors (SVG DOM)

Export bitmap (Canvas bitmap)

Previous work shows the best technology fit for the requirements 1, 2 and 3.a, but used server-side rendering for 3.b requiring additional components. In the next section we show and evaluate a method to use browsers native rendering of SVG to rasterize image in order to solve the interface requirement 3.b and exporting of rasterized image requirement 4.b.

Our Implementations

Following two methods allow native, two-way interaction with SVG and Canvas. A proposal for better and standardized implementation for SVG to Canvas is given in the "Recommendations" section of this paper after the security issues associated with it are presented.

Canvas to SVG

This method we presented last year [TRIVIAL09] and is provided here for completeness.

function importCanvas(sourceCanvas, targetSVG) {
    var img_dataurl = sourceCanvas.toDataURL("image/png");
    var svg_img = document.createElementNS(
        "http://www.w3.org/2000/svg", "image");

    svg_img.setAttributeNS(
        "http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink", "xlink:href", img_dataurl);

    targetSVG.appendChild(svg_img);
}

TODO: Could not get comments to be parsed in XML ?, need to write short overview.

SVG to Canvas

The idea for our "SVG to Canvas" method is to make use of the web browser rendering of SVG. As the SVG is rasterized in the screen, it should be possible to use those pixels directly in Canvas. However, no direct interface exists (yes, see our SVG.toDataURL() API recommendation in section "Recommendations"), so we’ll use Canvas for the job.

function importSVG(sourceSVG, targetCanvas) {
   // https://developer.mozilla.org/en/XMLSerializer
   svg_xml = (new XMLSerializer()).serializeToString(sourceSVG);
   var ctx = targetCanvas.getContext('2d');

   // this is just a JavaScript (HTML) image
   var img = new Image();
   // http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SVG#Native_support
   // https://developer.mozilla.org/en/DOM/window.btoa
   img.src = "data:image/svg+xml;base64," + btoa(svg_xml);

   img.onload = function() {
       // after this, Canvas’ origin-clean is DIRTY
       ctx.drawImage(img, 0, 0);
   }
}

Web browsers only expose the SVG data in DOM, which can also be serialized to XML. We used this in your last years implementation where we sent the serialized XML to server-side rasterizer, which returned a PNG image (with transparency).

Canvas allows to draw arbitrary images on it via the drawImage-function. The Canvas specification for drawImage() says: "The image argument is an instance of either HTMLImageElement, HTMLCanvasElement, or HTMLVideoElement." So any image that the browser supports, can be drawn on Canvas [CANVAS10].

All browsers support images with data URI [RFC2397]. Currently, some browsers (Webkit) support SVG images as source for img elements [SVGimg10]. By combining these, we can transfer the serialized XML SVG data into a HTML Image element. This HTML Image element can be used as an argument for the drawImage()-method of Canvas.

Currently (2010-08) this only works in Safari and Chrome. Also, the "SVG to Canvas" transfer is write-only, as it triggers the origin-clean flag of Canvas as dirty, which causes that Canvas to be unreadable (until reloaded and cleared). This security issue will be discussed in the "Security Issues" section.

Browser Compatibility

Support for the techniques used in the "Canvas to SVG" method are better and more consistent than for the "SVG to Canvas" methods, as can be seen from the table below.

Table 1: Browser compatibility for Canvas-SVG interaction

Quirk / Browser | Safari 4.1 (Webkit) | Chrome TODO.TODO (Webkit) | Firefox 3.6.x | Opera 10.x.x (TODO?) | IE 9 Preview xxxx TODO
XML-serialize dynamic SVG data | ok | ok | ok | ok | fail
Data URL in HTML img element | ok | ok | ok | ok | ok
SVG Image in HTML img element | ok | ok | fail | only static? |
Non-standard btoa() base64 function | ok | ok | ok | ok |
SVG data URL for Canvas drawImage | ok | ok | fail | fail |
...above should set origin-clean as dirty | ok | ok | ok | ok |
Canvas.toDataURL() | ok | ok | ok | ok | ok
extra: Right-click on Canvas allows "Save as.." | not | not | ok | not | TODO

Security Issues

Our "SVG to Canvas" approach has a security issue that could, however, be avoided as we argue in our SVG.toDataURL() proposal.

Same Origin and Canvas Origin Policy

Web pages are composed of different elements coming from different origins. Elements coming from the same origin are considered to be safe [Origin10].

Canvas has powerful image reading and writing capabilities. It would be trivial to use canvas as middleman for transfering a local image to a third-party just by loading image into Canvas element from file:// -URL and then sending the pixel data from the Canvas element to any host with JavaScript.

To prevent information leakage with Canvas, browsers are carefully protecting the usage of Canvas when the source for image data is not safe. All Canvas elements are created as their origin-clean attribute set to true. When any of the actions that may potentially be used for using Canvas element to transfer content that violates the same origin policy, the origin-clean property is permanently set to false.

If methods that return the pixel data stored in canvas, such as toDataURL() or getImageData(), are called on the Canvas element whose origin-clean is false, then a DOMException 18, SECURITY_ERR is raised [Canvas10].

Experimenting with Origin-Clean and Canvas

To get better understanding of origin-clean behaviour, we evaluated following cases.

PNG and drawImage()

We test following two trivial cases first:

Case 1a: load a PNG image to the DOM, draw that on Canvas element with drawImage()-method.

Case 1b: load a PNG image to the DOM, create an instance of JavaScript Image-object and draw that on Canvas element with drawImage()-method

In 1a and 1b, the Canvas element stays origin-clean as expected. JavaScript Image-object, as long as the MIME type is image/png works also. It seems like all MIME types other than image/svg+xml works this way.

Case 1c: Load an image from local file://-URL and display it on HTML document loaded from file://-URL. Then draw that image on Canvas element with drawImage()-method.

In 1c the Canvas element is not origin-clean. No data can be exported from Canvas, any attempts will cause a SECURITY_ERR exception. This the standard behavior that was changed lately in all browsers, like in Mozilla Gecko [MozillaSameOrigin].

PNG as Data URI

When a PNG is represented as data URI so that img-elements source attribute is set to data URI: img.src = "data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0..." and this img-element is rendered on Canvas with drawImage()-method, the canvas stays origin-clean.

SVG to Canvas

If the source attribute of HTML img-element is set to "shapes.svg", and this image element is rendered on Canvas element, the origin-clean is set to false even if same origin policy should be satisfied.

SVG as Data URI

If the SVG is represented as a data URI: "data:image/svg+xml;base64,dVAx..." and this string is set as source attribute of a HTML image, which is then rendered on Canvas element, the origin-clean sets to false.

SVG with Safe Elements

This testing becomes more interesting if we do the same tests with a SVG that uses only safe elements, such as <rect> and <circle>. Result will be that the Canvas origin-clean property sets permanently to false, even if all the elements can be considered as "safe" and same origin.

Conclusions on SVG Security Issues

So, why SVG is dangerous? SVG can potentially contain content from multiple origins and browsers tend to blacklist any content with the MIME type image/svg+xml as multi-origin content without even testing the actual content. A good summary of this is given in the comments of Webkit bug #29305 "Canvas drawn with data URL image raises SECURITY_ERR when toDataUrl() called." on why browser needs to consider SVG as multi-origin content.

SVG that contains only safe and same origin elements should however be rendered to make allow efficent use of SVG with Canvas. In the next section we propose a recommendation for a SVG.toDataURL()-method that allows bitmap export of the vector elements in SVG.

Recommendations

SVG.toDataURL() API

Based on the use cases stated in the requirements for a complete drawing application in the web and the security discussion, we propose a following API to allow exporting of the bitmap content of the SVG.

SVG.toDataURL( [type], [keepNonSafe=false], [keepOutsideViewport=false] )

type
MIME type of the exported data.
Default: image/svg+xml.
Must support: image/png.
keepNonSafe
Export non-safe (image and foreignObject) elements and set the Canvas origin-clean property to false.
Default: false (to keep origin-clean true)
keepOutsideViewport
Export all drawn content, even if not visible.
Default: false, export only visible viewport, similar to Canvas toDataURL()

For Browser Manufacturers

In addition to SVG.toDataURL()-method presented above, we would like to see following improvments in browsers.

Safari, Chrome (Webkit) and Opera

Clicking Canvas with right-click should prompt for "save as" (PNG). This is the easiest way to export anything that has been drawn on Canvas.

Firefox

Support for SVG files as source for img-element.

Opera

Fix dynamic SVG in img-element support, what ever that means (TODO)

Internet Explorer

XMLSerializer (XMLSerializer) is needed for the browser.

SVG Compatibility Workarounds

SVG 1.1 recommendation is seven years old, but still not very well supported [SvgSupport]. Good statistics on SVG support can be seen at http://www.codedread.com/svg-support.php. To address the lacking support for SVG and the security issue presented above, a great number of projects has spawned trying to implement SVG rendering with other technologies.

Alternative technologies to render SVG are Canvas, Flash and VML. In the following list we have tried to gather all compatibility workarounds and other related projects of this field. At the end of this section some notes on problems associated with the workarounds are given.

CanVG

http://code.google.com/p/canvg/

CanVG is the most feature complete SVG compatibility JavaScript library for browsers that support Canvas. The projects end goal is to support everything in the SVG specification. And currently CanVG is selected for the SVG-Edit to solve SVG rasterization. We will evaluate the usage of CanVG later in this paper.

SVG Web

http://code.google.com/p/svgweb/

SVG Web renders SVG files with Adobe Flash. At the time of writing it supports ~50% of the SVG 1.1 specification [SvgSupport].

CakeJS

http://code.google.com/p/cakejs/wiki/Documentation#SVGParser

The Canvas Animation JavaScript library CakeJS has implemented SVG parser that converts SVG DOM to its own set of drawing commands that can be used to rasterize and animate SVG elements on Canvas.

Raphaël, Dojox.gfx and SVGKit SVGCanvas

http://raphaeljs.com/
http://docs.dojocampus.org/dojox/gfx
http://svgkit.sourceforge.net/SVGCanvas.html

Raphaël and dojox.gfx do not implement SVG compatibility, but rather provide own API that can be used for drawing vector graphics. Raphaël is a JavaScript library that provides Canvas like API for drawing graphics. It uses SVG for drawing graphics and falls back to VML if the browser does not support SVG).

Dojox.gfx is an extension to the Dojo toolkit that similary to Raphaël uses SVG and VML, but also Silverlight and Canvas for drawing vector graphics.

SVGKits SVGCanvas is also mentioned, because it provides Canvas API implementation that is rendered with SVG.

Flanvas

http://flanvas.com/

"Flanvas provides a way of interactive development similar to flex. The hope is that actionscript developers will find this to be an easy solution to use when flash is either too much, or not available."

Flanvas parses SVG files and creates own representation of them that can be animated. Support for SVG is still limited.

Abandoned CanvaSVG

http://web.archive.org/web/20070928172356/http%3a//fuchsia-design.com/CanvaSVG/

In order this listing to be more or less complete, it’s important to include already abandoned hack project to stress the fact that Canvas is very lucrative platform for developers to start implementing SVG support.

PNG Rasterization

Static SVGs can also be rasterized as PNG images that are displayed instead of the SVG files. This allows modifications still to be done on SVGs while providing full browser support. Wikipedia uses this technique to display their great amount of SVG images: http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/f/f2/Butterfly.svg/398px-Butterfly.svg.png.

Problems with Workarounds

There should not be any need to re-implement, but while native rendering support is missing, the following aspects should be considered.

Scene Graph is Missing with Canvas

In order to have interactivity with "vectorized" elements on Canvas, the implementation needs to keep track of the elements, their boundaries and ordering. This brings some overhead as discussed in our previous paper [TRIVIAL09].

Accessibility

More important than scene graph is the accessibility of the web. Especially with workaround solutions where the source is not available as SVG, but only as a non-accessible bitmap the accessibility is very limited.

Speed and Complexity

Not only the full support of SVG is quite complex task to complete with JavaScript and Canvas or Flash, but it is also more likely to be slower than a native implementation.

Guideline for Drawing Application Technologies

Based on the requirements stated above, here is our list of implementation recommendations for the current state of technologies. This is due to change in future, when better solutions become available.

Guideline and the Demonstration Page

See our demonstration page. TODO.

Our demonstration page shows a list of feature requirements for a complete drawing application with SVG and Canvas. Each of the requirements are implemented with most suitable methods. As the method used might effect on the other methods (by making them no longer available for security reasons), the page shows the effects: if a method is no longer available, it is rendered as TODO in the feature list. Refreshing the page resets the status.

Guideline Evaluation

If any TODO

Conclusions

The future web that is based on open web standards is not complete without fully supported vector graphics. Since the last SVG Open 2009, the popularity of SVG has not raised, but the support has become better, especially with the latest Internet Explorer 9 preview releases.

The list of compatibility libraries in this paper show that SVG a) SVG rendering support has to get better, and more interestingly b) the interaction with different technologies, like Canvas needs to improve as well. If browsers would support better interaction with SVG, with such features as our proposed toDataURL()-method, it would make SVG less isolated. As SVG has powerful features, the security issues that come with SVG need to be understood. The current security model is too thight for effective interaction with SVG.

Bibliography

[TRIVIAL09] Samuli Kaipiainen and Matti Paksula: SVG vs Canvas on Trivial Drawing Application.
Proceedings of the 7th International Conference on Scalable Vector Graphics
http://svgopen.org/2009/papers/54-SVG_vs_Canvas_on_Trivial_Drawing_Application/

[ISSUE70] SVG-Edit Issue #70: Ability to save canvas as PNG.
SVG-Edit Project
http://code.google.com/p/svg-edit/issues/detail?id=70

[CANVAS10] HTML5 Draft Standard 20: The canvas element, August 2010.
Web Hypertext Application Technology Working Group
http://www.whatwg.org/specs/web-apps/current-work/multipage/the-canvas-element.html

[RFC2397] RFC2397 The "data" URL scheme, August 1998.
The Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)
http://www6.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2397.txt

[SVGimg10] Wikipedia SVG: Native Support.
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SVG#Native_support

[Origin10] HTML5 Draft Standard 20: Origin, August 2010.
Web Hypertext Application Technology Working Group
http://www.whatwg.org/specs/web-apps/current-work/multipage/origin-0.html#same-origin

[MozillaSameOrigin] Same-origin policy for file: URIs
Mozilla Developer Center
https://developer.mozilla.org/En/Same-origin_policy_for_file:_URIs

[SvgSupport] SVG Support tables
Codedread
http://www.codedread.com/svg-support.php